Connie Nappier Jr. Papers VHP2006/32
CCSU Veterans History Project
Connie Nappier Jr. Papers
2006
VHP2006/32
CCSU Veterans History Project
287.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of Connie Nappier Jr. during World War II. He served as the "Tuskegee Airmen", the first African American military aviators in the United States armed forces. The collection contains personal service records, military correspondence, publications about Tuskegee Airmen, photographs, and an oral history interview.
Nappier, Connie, Jr., 1922 -
Biographical/Historical note
Connie Nappier, Jr. enlisted in the U.S. Army Air Corps after graduating high school in 1943. He wanted to be part of the Tuskegee Experiment, the program the Air Corps had set up to train African American fighter pilots. After endured grueling ground training at Tuskegee Air Field, he and a few other soldiers were informed that their services were needed as bombardier navigators. He and group of others from Tuskegee Air Field were sent to Midland, Texas to complete the flight and ground training as bombardier navigators. It was during this time that Nappier was given his "wings", and made an officer, and the 477th medium bomb group was formed, which was a segregated bomb group. Nappier was a Flight Officer in the 477th, when the soldiers were transferred to Freeman Field in Indiana. At Freeman Field, 101 officers of the 477th Bomb Group were arrested for disobeying the Jim Crow laws that were established by Col. Selway, the base's commanding officer. Col. Selway had the men arrested, Nappier among them, and sent to the stockade at Goodman Field in Kentucky. It wasn't until an order was received from President Truman that the officers were released. Nappier then returned to Tuskegee Air Field to finish his pilot training. He had dreamed of becoming a pilot since childhood. He was part of the 46D class, which was the last pilot class trained at Tuskegee. Unfortunately, the war ended, and the pilots' training was not completed. Nappier was discharged from the Air Corps, and he returned home to Hartford, Ct, where he used the G.I. Bill to complete his education as an architect. In 2007, after this interview was recorded, Nappier received the Congressional Gold Medal in Washington, D.C. alongside other veterans from Tuskegee Air Field.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Army Air Corps.; United States. Army Air Forces. Bombardment Squadron, 616th.; United States. Army Air Forces. Composite Group, 477th.; United States. Army Air Forces.; Freeman Field (Ind.); Freeman Field Mutiny, Ind., 1945.; Keesler Air Force Base (Miss.); Mitchell bomber; Tuskegee Airmen, Inc; Tuskegee Army Air Field (Ala.); World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945--African Americans
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/32.I
  - Letter of recommendation from Charles Gipson, coach at Weaver High School, April 29, 1943; VHP2006/32.I.1
  - Letter of recommendation from Frank Burki, Pricipal of Weaver High School, April 30, 1943; VHP2006/32.I.2
  - Letter of recommendation from Allen Jackson, M. D., May 23, 1943; VHP2006/32.I.3
  - U.S. Government Bill of Landing Memorandum, July 13, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.4
  - Chart Issue Record, Army Air Force Bombardier School, TX, July 1944; VHP2006/32.I.5
  - Army Air Force Bombardier School's trainning equipments charge out reciept, July 1944; VHP2006/32.I.6
  - Army Air Force Bombardier School's trainning equipments charge out reciept, September 11, 1944; VHP2006/32.I.7
  - Enlistment and discharge records, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.8; 4.0 Digital objects
  - Telegram to Connie Nappier about transfer order to 477th Bomb Group, December 5, 1944; VHP2006/32.I.9
  - Form pertaining to return of flying clothing, May 22, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.10
  - Form pertaining to issuance of flying clothing, January 24, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.11
  - Letter, subject: Nav. Alert Office of the day, February 28, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.12
  - Leave of absence letter, March 4, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.13
  - Letter, subject: Privately Owned Motor Vehicle, March 15, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.14
  - Letter, subject:Request for pilot training, March 24, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.15
  - Officers Clearance Sheet, Account of Nappier, Connie, Jr., April 3, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.16
  - Officer’s Final Clearance Certificate, April 3, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.17
  - Letter, subject:"Request for Individal Coursel", April 17, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.18
  - Letter, subject: Request for individual Counsel, April 17, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.19
  - Letter, Request for individual counsel disapproved, April 21, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.20
  - Letter, subject: Administrative Reprimand, April 24, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.21
  - Pay and Allowance Account, April 24, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.22
  - Letter, subject: Request for Pilot Training, May 2, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.23
  - Letter, subject: "Delinquiency", May 10, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.24
  - Letter, Basic request disapproved, May 15, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.25
  - Form Pertaining to Return of Flying Clothing, June 22, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.26
  - AAF Personal Affairs Statement, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.27; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Report of Departure, June 24, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.28; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Letter of receipt, July 26, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.29; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Pilot’s Log, August - November 1945; VHP2006/32.I.30; 7.0 Digital objects
  - Memorandum Receipt, September1945; VHP2006/32.I.31
  - Pay and Allowance Account, October 17, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.32
  - Clearance letter, October 18, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.33
  - Letter: subject: Delinquent Accounts, November 19, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.34
  - Letter, subject: Unsatisfactory Progress, November 20, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.35
  - Order to report, November 21, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.36
  - Leave of absence letter, November 23, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.37
  - Receipt for Miscellaneous Collections, December 31, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.38
  - Letter to City Police Court, Hartford, Conn., March 5, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.39; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Affidavit, May 1946; VHP2006/32.I.40; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Letter, subject: Relief from Active Duty, May 9, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.41
  - Request for Shipment of Authorized Baggage, June 27, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.42
  - Arrival Notice, July 29, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.43
  - Notice of Exception, June 2, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.44
  - Notice of Authorization of Subsistence Allowance, October 15, 1946; VHP2006/32.I.45; 2.0 Digital objects
  - US Civil Service Commission Notice Of Rating, January 7, 1950; VHP2006/32.I.46
  - Letter of recommendation from the judge of City Police Court, Hartford, Connecticut, circa 1950; VHP2006/32.I.47
  - POM training for officers form, circa 1945; VHP2006/32.I.48
  - Certificate of Training, circa 1945; VHP2006/32.I.49
  - Officers’ Post Clearance, July 25, 1945; VHP2006/32.I.50
  - Request letter, December 1945; VHP2006/32.I.51
  - Connie Nappier Jr. 's dog tags, circa 1945; VHP2006/32.I.52
  - Oral history interview synopsis, March 15, 2006; VHP2006/32.I.53; 2.0 Digital objects
- Series II: Military Documents, VHP2006/32.II
  - Special orders number 159, June 7, 1944; VHP2006/32.II.1; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Training orders number 61, July 7, 1944; VHP2006/32.II.2; 5.0 Digital objects
  - Personnel orders number 31, November 1, 1944; VHP2006/32.II.3; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 289, December 1, 1944; VHP2006/32.II.4; 7.0 Digital objects
  - Letter to graduating class, December 2, 1944; VHP2006/32.II.5; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 169, December 28, 1944; VHP2006/32.II.6; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 15, January 31, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.7; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 58, February 27, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.8; 6.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 72, March 13, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.9; 4.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 91, April 1, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.10; 29.0 Digital objects
  - Letter, subject: Disciplinary Action, April 11, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.11
  - Special orders number 87, April 12, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.12
  - Letter, subject: Disciplinary Action, April 12, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.13; 3.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 101, May 4, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.14; 8.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 147, June 21, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.15; 7.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 206, July 25, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.16; 8.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 190, August 6, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.17; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Letter, subject: Extra Duty for Student Officers, September 19, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.18
  - Special orders number 255, October 19, 1945; VHP2006/32.II.19; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 111, May 10, 1946; VHP2006/32.II.20; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 127, June 4, 1946; VHP2006/32.II.21; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 141, June 24, 1946; VHP2006/32.II.22; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Special orders number 186, July 5, 1946; VHP2006/32.II.23; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Letter from the Office of the State Treasurer, June 6, 1975; VHP2006/32.II.24; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Memorandum: Don'ts in Saluting, VHP2006/32.II.25; 3.0 Digital objects
  - Operation instructions for Non-Metallic Personal 201 File, n.d.; VHP2006/32.II.26; 3.0
  - Care of Parachute sheet, n.d.; VHP2006/32.II.27; 3.0
  - Letter excerpts on allotments, n.d.; VHP2006/32.II.28; 3.0
- Series III: Publications, VHP2006/32.III
  - Tony Brown’s Journal: the Story of America's Black Air Force, 1983; VHP2006/32.III.1; 15.0 Digital objects
  - An Evening with the Tuskegee Airmen, April 28, 2001; VHP2006/32.III.2; 6.0 Digital objects
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2006/32.IV
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/32.IV
    - 2nd Lt. Bertram Wilson, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.1
    - 2nd Lt. Edward T. Hall, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.2
    - 2nd Lt. John Roach, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.3
    - Captain Lemuel Rodney Custis, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.4
    - Captain Roscoe Brown, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.5
    - Eleanor Roosevelt & Charles Anderson, 30 min flight, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.6
    - Flight Officer Connie Nappier Jr., circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.7
    - General Benjamin O. Davis Jr., circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.8
    - General Daniel “Chappie” James, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.9
    - L to R: Captains Erwin Lawrence (KIA 1944) & Lemuel Rodney Custis, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.10
    - Prisoners of War, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.11
    - P-51 Mustang "Red Tail" (and beyond), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.12
      Scope and Contents note
      The Tuskegee Airmen were forced to operate as segregated units and not allowed to train or fight alongside their white fellow countrymen. To identify themselves they painted the tails of their aircraft red, thus becoming the "Red Tails". The Tuskegee Airmen "Red Tails" carried their hopes and dreams of equality for themselves and their thirteen million African American countrymen into battle. Source: The CAF Red Tail Project. http://www.redtail.org/airmen.html
    - Tuskegee Airmen and his plane, the Red Tail with damage on the wing, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.13
    - Modern day air craft [F-16?] with tail painted red, VHP2006/32.IV.14
    - P-51 Mustangs "Red Tails" preparing for take off, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.15
    - P-51 Mustang "Red Tail" with airman sitting on the wing, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.16
    - Airman working on propeller of P-51 Mustangs, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.17
    - P-51 Mustangs parked on airfield, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.18
    - P-51 Mustang with red tail, n.d.; VHP2006/32.IV.19
    - Airman posted with P-51 Mustang, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.20
    - Three P51-Mustangs flying, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.21
    - Red Tail Squadron, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.22
    - P-51 Mustang "Red Tail", n.d.; VHP2006/32.IV.23
    - Tuskegee Air Field (View of P-40 Ramp), Sep. 22, 1944; VHP2006/32.IV.24
    - Tuskegee Airman getting out of a cokpit, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.25
    - Unidentified Tuskegee Airman, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.26
    - Unidentified Tuskegee Airman, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.27
    - Tuskegee Airmen (Class pictures), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.28
    - Tuskegee Airmen (Initial Mission Debrief), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.29
    - Picture of Tuskegee Airmen in newspaper article, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.30
    - Picture of Tuskegee Airmen in newspaper article, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.31
    - Tuskegee Airman holding Coke bottle, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.32
    - Tuskegee Airman with airplane in background, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.33
    - Group od Tuskegee Airmen in dress uniform, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.34
    - Tuskegee Airmen talking (Swapping Stories), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.35
    - Tuskegee Airmen (Training Squadron II), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.36
    - Tuskegee Airmen (Training Squadron), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.37
    - Tuskegee Airmen in training, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.38
    - Tuskegee Airmen in War Bonds Poster, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.39
    - Tuskegee Airmen (Win first Red Flag), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.40
    - Tuskegee Airmen Crew, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.41
    - Tuskegee Airmen Crew, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.42
    - Tuskegee Airmen Crew, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.43
    - Tuskegee Airmen (99th Flighter Squadron 1942), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.44
    - Tuskegee Airmen, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.45
    - Tuskegee Airmen (Class 44-F), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.46
    - Tuskegee Airmen (The 99th Flying Squadron 1942), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.47
    - Tuskegee Airmen Class 44G, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.48
    - Tuskegee Bomber (B-25 Mitchell Bomber), circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.49
    - Tuskegee Maintenance Airmen, circa 1940s; VHP2006/32.IV.50
    - Connie Nappier, Jr. at time of interview. New Britain, CT, March 15, 2006; VHP2006/32.IV.51
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/32.IV (Disk DVD VHP2006/32, Box VHP Interview 2006)
    - Oral history interview, March 15, 2006; VHP2006/32.IVb.1; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen